Guide to the Susan Wicklund papers RL.11321
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Susan Wicklund papers
1970-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wicklund, Susan
RL.11321
8 Linear Feet 16 boxes
Dr. Susan Wicklund is a former abortion provider from Wisconsin. The papers chiefly document her professional career, centering on her work in the Midwest, where she operated abortion clinics in Minnesota, Montana, North Dakota, and Wisconsin from the 1990s to 2013. Materials include many items of correspondence from patients, supporters, and opponents; files on national and local abortion rights and women's movement groups; articles and newspaper clippings; conference papers; materials related to anti-abortion groups; legal documents, including court case records; a recording of her 1992 "60 Minutes" television interview, and drafts of her book, This Common Secret: My Journey as an Abortion Doctor (2007). A few clinic documents also exist in the form of leasing records, sample charts, manuals, and anonymized guestbooks. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in the original order in which they were received.
Biographical / Historical
Susan Wicklund was born in 1954 and spent her career as an abortion provider in the Midwest. In her early twenties, she herself received an abortion just three years after the procedure was legalized. Her experience was relatively traumatic due in part to the apathy of the providers. This inspired her to pursue a career in medicine so that she could one day be the kind of abortion provider she wished she had when she underwent the procedure. She opened her own clinic in 1993, after which she faced constant threats from anti-abortion groups, and was targeted as a murderer of children. Despite fearing for her life, she continued practicing until 2013, when she retired and closed her clinic, the Mountain Country Women's Clinic in Livingston, Montana. She recounts her experiences in her own words in her book This Common Secret: My Journey as an Abortion Doctor, which was published in 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual media is closed to use. Access copies may be requested in advance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Susan Wicklund papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016.
Content Description
The Susan Wicklund papers include personal correspondence and professional papers regarding her work as an abortion provider in Minnesota, Montana, North Dakota, and Wisconsin. Materials relate mostly to her work at Mountain Country Women's Clinic in Livingston, Montana in the 1990s, and include newspaper clippings, letters of support, patient reviews, donations, and administrative documents relating to the clinic in the form of sample charts, manuals, and anonymized guestbooks.
Materials relating to Wicklund's 1992 television interview on the "60 Minutes" program include a VHS tape of the interview, clippings, and many letters of support as well as hate mail.
The collection also contains materials related to anti-abortion groups and their harassment of Wicklund; these records also include legal documents referring to a related court case.
Also present in the collection are materials about various women's health organizations, support groups, conferences, and other clinics and centers, including Planned Parenthood, National Women's Organization, and the National Abortion Rights Action League. Drafts of Wicklund's book, This Common Secret: My Journey as an Abortion Doctor (2007) are also in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains sensitive information. Contact the Rubenstein Library for access: https://duke.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_8fblaT2NbgbQujj
Abortion -- Religious aspects; Abortion -- United States; Abortion services -- Middle West; Abortion services -- United States -- History; Pro-choice movement--United States; Pro-life movement -- United States; Women's health services -- Law and legislation -- United States; Women's health services -- United States; Middle West -- Social conditions; VHS; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Wicklund, Susan
- CV and background, 1970s-1980s (Box 1)
- Family, undated (Box 1)
- Education, 1972-1987 (Box 1)
- Diplomas and certificates, 1980s (Box 1)
- Personal correspondence, 1982-2010 and undated (Box 1)
- Poems, undated (Box 1)
- Grantsburg Clinic, October 5, 1988 (Box 1)
- Fox Valley Reproductive Health Care Center [Wisconsin], July 15, 1989 (Box 1)
- FWHO/SWHO, 1991-1992 and undated (Box 1)
- Calendars NWHO (Box 2)
- Rally Cambridge, MN, 1991 (Box 2)
- FWHO v. Lambs of Christ, 1991-1998 (Box 2)
- House Bill 1579, informed consent, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
- Legal papers – Fargo, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
- Clinic Defense Project, Fargo, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- Newspaper coverage, Fargo, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
- Cambridge Star clippings, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
- City Pages, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
- Fargo Forum, 1989-1992, undated (Box 2)
- Inter-County Leader (Polk and Burnett Counties, Wisconsin) clippings, 1989-1992 (Box 2)
- Milwaukee Journal clippings, 1992 (Box 2)
- Milwaukee Sentinel clippings, 1989-1992 (Box 2)
- Articles by Martina Greywind (Box 2)
- March for Women's Lives, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- Pro-Choice movement materials, 1991-1995, undated (Box 2)
- The Doctor-Activist materials (book, 1997), 1992 (Box 2)
- Letters of support, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
- Letters of support, January 1992 - July 1992 (Box 3)
- Donation, 1992 (Box 3)
- Anti-abortion letters, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
- MCWC, Bozeman, Montana (Mountain Country Women's Clinic), 1993-1998 (Box 3)
- MCWC Clinic forms (Box 4)
- Correspondence, Dr. Balice, Bozeman, Montana, 1992-1995 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, MCWC, Bozeman, Montana, 1993-1997 (Box 4)
- Tkach, 1992 (Box 4)
- Questionnaire (Box 4)
- MCWC, Bozeman, Montana, calls to clinic, 1990s? (Box 16)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Personal medical information restricted.
- Correspondence, Graybill (attorney), 1993 (Box 4)
- FACE (Freedom of Access to Clinic Entrances), 1993-1995 (Box 4)
- Coalition for Life v. Janet Reno [FACE Challenge] (Box 4)
- Anti-abortion letters, 1993-1997 (Box 4)
- Anti-abortion, Michael Ross, 1993-2012 (Box 4)
- Michael Ross, correspondence and clippings, 1994-2012 (Box 4)
- MCWC, contracts/rent documents, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
- Abortion referral feedback, 1994 (Box 4)
- MCWC budget narrative, 1997 (Box 4)
- Max Baucus, US Senate, 1993-1997, undated (Box 4)
- Yankowski, 1997 (Box 5)
- Conrad Burns, US Senate, 1993-1994 (Box 5)
- Senate Bill 292, 1995 (Box 5)
- Montana Parental Notification Lawsuit, 1993-2012 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, Fay Clayton, 1998-2010 (Box 5)
- Letters of support, 1993-1994 (Box 5)
- Letters of support, 1995-1999 (Box 6)
- P.R.O. Filmworks, 1992 (Box 6)
- Correspondence with writers, 1992-1995 (Box 6)
- New Woman magazine, "People of the Year", 1992 (Box 6)
- Native American Reproductive Rights Council, Pierre, South Dakota, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
- Minnesota Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights, 1993 (Box 6)
- Women Aloud, 1993 (Box 6)
- Elizabeth Blackwell Health Center for Women, 1993 (Box 6)
- Coalition Against Clinic Violence and Harassment, Des Moines, Iowa, 1993 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, literary agents, 1993-1994 (Box 6)
- NARAL (National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League) Awards Celebrations - Voices for Choice, 1994 (Box 6)
- NOW (National Organization for Women) Montana State conference, 1993-1994 (Box 6)
- Mirabella, 1992-1994 (Box 6)
- Yorkshire TV, 1993-1994 (Box 6)
- Correspondence with film producers, 1994-1995 (Box 6)
- Correspondence with Rickie Sollinger, 1994-1995 (Box 6)
- Glamour magazine article, 1995 (Box 7)
- Glamour magazine proposal, 1997 (Box 7)
- New Woman magazine article by Wicklund: An Abortion Doctor's Hardest Choices (March 1999), 1998-1999 (Box 7)
- March for Women's Lives, 2004 (Box 7)
- This Common Secret, book proposal packet (Box 7)
- Book drafts 2-5 (Box 7)
- Book draft 6 (Box 8)
- Book manuscript, 2007 (Box 8)
- This Common Secret, page proofs (Box 8)
- Wicklund-Kesselheim Correspondence (Box 8)
- Sue's story (Box 8)
- Speaking notes, undated (Box 8)
- This Common Secret, letters from readers, 2008 (Box 8)
- Ms. magazine, 2007-2010 (Box 8)
- Speaking invitations, 1992-2011 (Box 8)
- Book tours, publicity, reviews (Box 9)
- Interview requests, 1992 (Box 9)
- Media Communication Guidance, 1990 (Box 9)
- MCWC, Livingston, 2008-2013 (Box 9)
- Sample chart, undated (Box 9)
- Wall hangings, MCWC Livingston, 2009-2013 (Box 9)
- Supporters of MCWC Livingston, 2009, undated (Box 9)
- American Rights Coalition, undated (Box 9)
- Anti-abortion materials (Box 9)
- MCWC guest books (Box 16)
  Collection contains sensitive information. Contact Research Services for Access: https://duke.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_8fblaT2NbgbQujj
- Picketer information [all clinics] (Box 9)
- Security alerts [all clinics] (Box 9)
- State Abortion Laws, 1989-2009 (Box 9)
- Thornburgh v. ACOG, 1985-1986 (Box 9)
- Doe v. Esch (Box 9)
- Jeanette R v. Ellery, 1995 (Box 9)
- Measure (Attorney), 1993-1994 (Box 9)
- Abortion counseling [Charlotte Taft], 2009, undated (Box 9)
- American Life League, 1991-1995 (Box 9)
- Ultrasound machine manual (Box 10)
- Bozeman Chronicle, letters to the editor (Box 10)
- Trust Women Fund, 2011 (Box 10)
- MCWC Open House, 2010 (Box 10)
- Anti-abortion letters, 2009-2013, undated (Box 10)
- Letters of support, 2000-2009 (Box 10)
- Letters of support, 2010-2013 (Box 11)
- Donations, 2011-2013 (Box 11)
- Letters of support, undated (Box 11)
- Form letters of support (Box 11)
- Form postcards of support (Box 11)
- Catholic Diocese of Duluth / Bishop Schwietz, 1990 (Box 11)
- Catholics for a Free Choice, 1990 (Box 11)
- Center for Reproductive Law and Policy, 1992-1998 (Box 12)
- Choices Women's Medical Center (Box 12)
- Clara Bell Duvall Education Fund, 1994 (Box 12)
- Feminist Majority Foundation, 1992-1998 (Box 12)
- Feminist Women's Health Center, 1998 (Box 12)
- FOCA (Freedom of Choice Act), 1992 (Box 12)
- Guttmacher Institute, 1992-2006 (Box 12)
- Warren Hern, Boulder Colorado (Box 12)
- Elizabeth Karlin, 1998 (Box 12)
- Life Dynamics, Inc., 1993-1994 (Box 12)
- Margaret Sanger Society, 1998-2001 (Box 12)
- Medical Students for Choice, 1992-1999, undated (Box 12)
- NAF (National Abortion Federation), 1992-1994 (Box 12)
- NAF and PPFA (Planned Parenthood Federation of America): "Undue Burden", 1993 (Box 12)
- NARAL (National Abortion Rights Action League), 1989-2009 (Box 12)
- NARAL Fundraising and Awards Celebrations, 2008-2009 (Box 12)
- NARAL Montana, 1989-2013, undated (Box 13)
- NARAL New York, 1995-2004 (Box 13)
- NARAL Oregon, 1996-1997 (Box 13)
- NCAP, 1992-1998 (Box 13)
- Networks Newsletter, 1992-1994 (Box 13)
- NOW (National Organization for Women), 1989-2007 (Box 13)
- National NOW Times, 1991-1995 (Box 13)
- Pearson Manual (Box 13)
- Physicians for Reproductive Choice and Health, 2005 (Box 13)
- Planned Parenthood, 1990-2008 (Box 13)
- PPFA Phoenix Talk, 1994 (Box 13)
- Pro-Life Action News, 1990-1992 (Box 13)
- Refuse & Resist!, 1996-2001 (Box 14)
- Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice, 1991-1995 (Box 14)
- Routh Street Women's Clinic (Box 14)
- Youth For America, 1991 (Box 14)
- The Body Politic, 1994 (Box 14)
- Brookwood, Toward a More Perfect Union, 1991 (Box 14)
- Cartoons (Box 14)
- Bozeman Chronicle clippings, 1993-2008, undated (Box 14)
- Life Advocate, 1992 (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous newsletters, 1992-1998 (Box 14)
- New York Times clippings, 1990-2007 (Box 14)
- St. Paul Pioneer press clippings, 1990-2006 (Box 14)
- Star Tribune clippings, 1989-1994 (Box 14)
- Wall Street Journal clippings, 1994-1995, undated (Box 14)
- Washington Post clippings, 1990-1993 (Box 14)
- General clippings, 1990-2009 (Box 15)
- General clippings, undated (Box 15)
- Articles on abortion and reproduction, 1985-2008 (Box 15)
- Abortion articles (non-medical), 1991-2013 (Box 15)
- Articles not related to abortion, 1984-1992 (Box 15)
- Email and online article printouts, 1999-2012 (Box 15)
- Mountain Country Clinic waiting room journals and guestbooks, 1993-2013 (Box 16)
- CBS "60 Minutes" television interview with Wicklund (VHS cassette), 1992 February (Box 16)
  Original media are restricted to use. Viewing copy is available by advance request.